上溯至宇宙初始 周遭还只是一片漆黑
In the beginning, there was darkness.
不知何时 忽地一声巨响
And then... Bang!
时间空间以及物质皆由此发端
Giving birth to an endless expanding existence
此后不断膨胀 延伸 永无止境
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在不断为我们解开
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking
蕴藏于这里的那些神秘莫测
the mysterious, the mind-blowing,
令人大开眼界 致命的秘密
the deadly secrets of a place we call
我们称这个地方为"宇宙"
the universe.
随着科学家们不断地解开宇宙之迷
As they try to unravel the mysteries of the universe,
他们正逐渐得出一个令人意外的结论
scientists are coming to an astounding conclusion.
要了解外部
To make sense of outer space,
就得先了解内部
they need to understand inner space,
微小的物质
the microscopic matter
是万物之源
that forms the foundation of everything we see.
让我们变小数十亿倍
But shrinking down billions of times,
去到原子和次原子粒子的领域
into the realm of atoms and subatomic particles,
进入一个奇异的陌生世界
takes us into a strange unexplored world.
当我们下到微观世界
When we descend into the microscopic world,
就会发现它是那么的不可思议
we find that it's really weird,
那么的离奇 让人难以置信
and indeed downright bizarre and unbelievable.
那里的东西
narrator: The stuff in this universe
远比用显微镜能看到的东西小
is far smaller than anything we can see with a microscope,
但它是整体的关键基础
but it holds the key to the cosmos.
只有了解这个离奇的微观世界
We can only understand where we came from
才能了解我们从哪里来
if we understand this crazy microworld.
因此 让我们展开一次神奇之旅
So let's go on a fantastic voyage
畅游微观宇宙
into an uncharted world
这一个未知的世界
known as the microscopic universe.
宇宙:微观宇宙
当人们说起宇宙
When people talk about the universe,
通常都是指跨度数十亿光年
they usually mean the vast expanse of space
可以通过射线望远镜
billions of light-years across
和宇宙成像技术看到的
that they can see with radio telescopes
广袤空间
and cosmic imaging.
人们会联想到恒星 星系和行星
They think about stars and galaxies and planets
以及那里所有的庞然大物
and all the big stuff out there.
那里有很多天体
You have astronomical bodies
在万有引力的作用下运转
moving under the force of gravity.
自然规律
There are laws of nature,
在其背后起作用
and you think that the laws are right,
永恒不变
once and for all.
然而 还存在另一种宇宙
However, there is another universe,
一个看不见的世界
an unseen world
在控制着我们看到的一切
that governs everything we see.
当我们变小数万亿倍
When we go down in size trillions of times smaller
去到微观世界
to the microscopic world,
那里的法则远远不同于
the rules are much less intuitive
我们通常对宏观世界的直觉认识
than the ones we're used to from the large-scale world.
微观宇宙的魔法
The magic of the microscopic universe
就发生在一个亿分之一米
begins at about a ten-billionth of a meter,
或者是原子大小的物质上
or the size of an atom.
这种状态下的物质 表现非常不同
Matter behaves so differently at this level
科学家们已经发现其运行的是
that scientists have developed an entirely new set of rules
一种全新的机制
to describe what's going on.
并称之为"量子论"
They call it quantum theory.
这个理论的内容非常特别
And what it says is extraordinary.
电子或光子这样的次原子粒子
This baseball represents a subatomic particle,
形状就象我手中的棒球
like an electron or a photon of light,
它们在微观宇宙里
that routinely does all sorts of weird,
构建成各种各样离奇古怪的东西
strange things in the microscopic universe.
如果棒球就是次原子
The subatomic version of this baseball
它就能隐身
can be invisible,
就能轻而易举地穿过固体物质
can go through solid objects with ease,
能够在同一瞬间去到各处
can be in multiple places at the same time,
并似乎能够时光倒流
and can seemingly go backwards in time
改变过去
and change the past.
这就意味着我把这个微小的棒球
This means I could throw this microscopic baseball
投到一垒和本垒 所花的时间一样
to first base and to home plate at the same time...
或是能够改变似乎铁定的比赛结果
or change the seemingly predetermined outcome of a play
哪怕比赛还在进行着
while it's still going on.
刚才只不过是科幻小说里的说法
Now this-this is the stuff of science fiction.
但实际上 次原子的事情是真的
But really, we know it to be true,
至少 在技术突飞猛进的今天
or at least, it appears to be true
它看起来真实可信
in our quantum world.
我们因此遇到了各种离奇的事情
We get all sorts of weird things happening.
如果科学家们能够知道
If scientists can understand
这些离奇事情的个中缘由
how these weird things work,
他们就能把它用在
they'll be able to put them to use
我们的日常生活
in our everyday world,
使现代计算机发生彻底变革
revolutionizing modern computing,
甚至可能会让我们在茫茫宇宙间
and perhaps even allowing us to communicate
实现即时通讯
across the cosmos instantly.
把这些神奇变为现实的关键过程
The key to making these miracles come true
被称为"量子纠缠"
is a process called quantum entanglement,
科学家们已经把
and scientists are already harnessing
这个惊人的发现
this astounding discovery
应用在民用和军用上
for both civilian and military purposes.
量子物理学认为
In quantum physics,
一个物体发生了变化
what happens to an object over here
就会立即影响那里的其它物体
can instantly affect an object over here,
哪怕物体之间相隔数百万英里
and over here could be millions of miles away.
其原理如下
This is how it works.
当两个次原子相互作用
When two subatomic particles interact,
它们会发生纠缠
they can become entangled.
这就意味着它们的旋转 位置
That means their spin, position,
或者是其它特性
or other properties become linked
通过一个现代科学尚未了解的方法 彼此关联
through a process unknown to modern science.
如果测量了其中一个粒子
If you then make a measurement of one of the particles,
那么你立即能确定
then that instantaneously determines
另一个粒子的状态
what the behavior of the other particle should be.
相关实验证明
And when the experiment is done,
确实如此
it's found that, indeed,
另一个粒子的量子态
the other particle's quantum state
会在你测量对应粒子的量子态时
is exactly determined once you've made a measurement
被确定下来
of the partner particle's quantum state.
这意味着
That means if a scientist
如果科学家让一个粒子
observes one entangled particle
按顺时针方向转动
and forces it to spin clockwise,
则与其纠缠的另一个粒子
the other entangled particle
将会立即朝反方向转动
will immediately start spinning in the opposite direction.
这个现象让人不但好奇 还非常震惊
That seems intriguing, but it's hardly earth-shattering
你想象一下 当两个纠缠的粒子
until you consider that the two entangled particles
被分隔开数百万光年之遥
can be separated by billions of light-years,
你研究其中一个粒子的旋转情况
and still, the moment you observe one particle's spin,
就能知道另一个粒子的旋转状态
you've dictated the other particle's spin.
这真是离奇
That's weird,
它让人想到信息会从一个粒子
because it may suggest that information has traveled instantaneously,
立刻传送到另一个粒子
faster than the speed of light,
快得超过了光速
from one particle to another.
我搞不懂它 也不知道谁会懂
I don't understand it. I don't know that anyone does.
"遥远的鬼魅行为" 爱因斯坦这样来形容它
"Spooky action at a distance," as Einstein called it.
量子纠缠
Quantum entanglement
不只是人们头脑中好奇的想法
is more than a curiosity of the microscopic world
在现实世界里
because the effects of entangled particles
纠缠粒子已经能被看到 被感觉到了
can be seen and felt in our world.
如果科学家能突破某些重大障碍
If scientists can overcome some fundamental obstacles,
将来有一天 量子纠缠会帮助人类
quantum entanglement could someday help humans
跨越遥远的距离 进行即时通信
communicate across vast distances instantly.
人们时常想着
People sometimes think that
量子纠缠会达成人们的渴望
quantum entanglement will achieve the desired goal
能够让信息传输
of transferring information
以快过光速的速度进行
at a speed faster than that of light.
我并不看好它
I don't think this will be achieved,
因为要建立这样的系统
because to set up these systems,
你只能以比光速慢的速度
you had to have brought them there at speeds
携带它们前往目的地
slower than the speed of light.
但谁说得清明天？
But then what do I know?
一百年前
A hundred years ago,
人们可没想过上月球呢
they didn't think that we'd be going to the Moon.
量子纠缠非常有可能
Quantum entanglement is far more likely
应用在现代计算机的变革上
to transform modern computing.
科学家们希望利用微观宇宙的神奇
Scientists hope to use the magic of the microscopic universe
去建立强大的新型计算机
to build powerful new computers.
我们去看看这个小家伙能做些什么
We're going to see what this baby can do.
在麻省理工学院
At the Massachusetts Institute of Technology,
希斯·罗埃德教授
Professor Seth Lloyd
建造了一台量子计算机的雏形
has helped create a prototype of a quantum computer
它使用的是量子比特
which uses quantum bits
而不是传统计算机的比特
rather than traditional computer bits
来执行计算任务
to perform its calculations.
这个实验室拥有世上最好的超导量子比特
This lab has the world's best superconducting quantum bit,
或称昆比特
or Q-bit, in it.
在使用昆比特进行量子计算时
And when we do quantum computations with Q-bits,
量子计算机
we can have the quantum computer
可以同时执行多重任务
do multiple tasks simultaneously.
它在做这件事的同时
It can do this, it can do that
也能做另一件事
at the same time.
它能够做"2+2"
It can add two plus two,
能够做"1+3"
it can add one plus three,
也能同时做这两个运算
and it can add those two things simultaneously.
一个单独的昆比特
The fact that a single Q-bit
能同时执行许多计算的事实
can perform many calculations at the same time
让量子计算机潜力无穷
gives the quantum computer the potential to be far more powerful
这绝非任何计算机可以比拟
than any computer ever imagined.
但就象20世纪50年代的传统计算机
Like traditional computers in the 1950s,
量子计算机现在还处于婴儿期
quantum computers are in their infancy today.
庞大的机器占据了许多房间
The machines take up large rooms
只能做非常简单的计算
and can do only the most basic calculations.
可是它们前途无量
But they hold great promise for the future.
量子计算机是出了名的离奇
Quantum physics is notoriously weird,
古怪 还违反了直觉
strange, and counterintuitive.
它利用普通计算机做不到的离奇方式
And so quantum computers use this weirdness to compute in ways
去进行计算
that classical computers can't.
其主要障碍在于
The major stumbling block
如何有效地去编码
is figuring out how to effectively code
让1和0
classical information
这两个经典的计算机信息
the ones and zeros that computers use
能通过纠缠粒子
in a way the microscopic universe can process it
在微观宇宙里获得处理
using entangled particles.
一旦科学家有解决之道
But when scientists figure that out,
量子计算机会彻底改变世界
quantum computers could transform the planet.
如果你有一台量子计算机
Even if you have a quantum computer
即使没有非常多的量子比特
with not that very many bits,
你也能做许多事情
you might still be able to do things
比如
Iike break all the codes
破解互联网上的所有代码
that people use to communicate on the internet.
或者你能解决有大量可变因素的
Or you could solve very difficult problems
非常棘手的问题
having gajillions of variables,
比如你要弄明白
Iike try to figure out
宇宙大爆炸是怎么一回事
what happened at the big bang.
这些已经让人难以置信
That may be hard to believe,
但微观宇宙还有更奇怪的事情
but the microscopic universe gets even stranger.
一个非常著名的量子物理试验
In fact, the most famous experiment in quantum physics
展示了一个物体能够同时出现在两个地方
shows how one object can be in two places at the same time,
这个结果吓了伟大的阿尔伯特.爱因斯坦一跳
a result that startled the great Albert Einstein.
在探索微观宇宙的时候
As scientists explore the microscopic universe,
科学家们发现它遵循的原理
they find it's governed by rules
让正常世界里的人
that are often incomprehensible
总是觉得难以理解
to those of us in the normal world.
毫不夸张地说
At the smallest scales imaginable,
没有多少人知道
not only does information
还有什么东西能快过光速
appear to travel faster than the speed of light,
但人类似乎总能明察秋毫
but human observation often seems to decide what happens.
在量子力学上
It seems like the behavior of quantum mechanical stuff
你注意它和不注意它
is different when we're looking at it
其表现绝然不同
than when we're not looking at it.
这个深奥的结论
This profound conclusion
源自"双缝实验"
comes from performing the double-hole experiment.
在一个世纪前 科学家们开始了首次试验
Scientists first conducted this experiment a century ago,
让光子穿过有两道狭缝的金属
firing photons of light through a metal plate with two slits.
光线通过狭缝
The light that went through the holes
投射到后面的屏幕上
hit a screen behind the plate.
我将用棒球来进行
I'm going to demonstrate the results
这个神奇实验
of this amazing experiment
演示其结果
with a bunch of baseballs
我们为此竖起一道屏障
and a barrier that we've set up
在上面开了两个洞
which has two holes in it.
现在 在正常的世界里
Now, normally, in the everyday world,
如果我把许多棒球扔过任意一个洞
if I throw baseballs through one hole or the other,
它们会在本垒后面的屏幕上
they'll form a predictable pattern on a screen
形成一个图案
that we've set up behind home plate.
它们会撞击在这边 或是那边
They'll be in one place or the other.
好了 让我们不断投出棒球去形成图案
Now, let's make that pattern with a whole bunch of baseballs.
我要借助于发球机的帮助
I'm going to use this pitching machine.
这是第一个
Here's the first one.
请注意看
Let's see what happens.
看到了吗？
Now, you see?
棒球从其中一个洞穿过后
The balls landed on the screen in two bunches,
几乎是直线地落到屏幕上 形成两个区域
pretty much along a direct line from each of the two holes.
这结果很正常 完全在意料之中
That's natural. That's what we expect.
但当我们进入到微观宇宙
But when we descend into the microscopic universe
使用电子
and use electrons,
这些比棒球小十亿倍的东西去进行实验
which are 10 trillion times smaller than baseballs,
我们会得到
we get a very different, odd result
非常不同的奇怪结果
when we perform this experiment...
其形成的图案 会让你联想到
A pattern that you would expect if these were waves
波浪在同一时间里
going through both holes at the same time
通过两个洞 并且发生自我干涉
and interfering with themselves.
我们都知道
Well, we usually think of electrons
电子是粒子
as being particles.
那么怎么会表现出波的特性呢？
So how can they exhibit wavelike properties?
实验结果让人百思不得其解
These test results were confounding.
电子在撞击屏幕之前
The electron was a particle
还是粒子
before it was fired at the screen;
但从屏幕上的图案来看
yet it formed a pattern on the screen
好象单个的电子
as if this single electron
在同一时刻通过了两个洞
had gone through both holes at the same time.
难道微观粒子
Does a microscopic particle
自发地克隆自己？
spontaneously clone itself in midai?
经过多年研究
After years of study,
科学家们还不能确定其中原因
scientists still don't know exactly what's happening.
可能最不可思议的事情
Probably the most magical thing
就是在量子物理中
is that in quantum physics,
一个物体可以同时存在于不止一个地方
an object can be in more than one place at the same time.
它居然能感觉到两个狭缝
It actually can sense both slits
并冲了过去
and actually go through
也就是说 它以量子力学的方式
and quantum-mechanically feel the structure
知道了两个狭缝的结构
of both slits in the experiment.
大多数物理学家认为 数学是很纯粹的工具
Most physicists agree that the math is quite solid
解决问题的能力无可争辩
and leads to solutions that are undeniable
而且可以用实验数据来确认
and can be confirmed with experimental measurements.
但发生了什么 如何发生
But exactly what is happening, and how,
才是人们争论的焦点
is a matter of debate.
为了弄清楚
To try to grasp
这个令人惊异的实验真相
this amazing experimental result,
科学家们决心观察清楚单个电子
scientists decided to observe how individual electrons behaved
在通过双缝时的表现
when they went through the double slit.
到底粒子怎么能
How exactly could a particle go through both holes
同时通过两个孔？
at the same time?
科学家们瞪起眼睛去观察
Scientists got a front-row seat
这些电子或是其它的次原子
to observe the strange behavior of these electrons
甚至包括光子 它们的的奇异表现
or other subatomic particles or even photons of light.
这些东西太小 不是真正的物质
Doesn't really matter, as long as they're small.
人们不仅观察它们
They didn't just look at where they landed
落到屏幕上的情况
on the screen back there;
也观察它们
they also watched the behavior of the particles
通过双缝时的情形
as they went through the holes.
惊人的一幕出现了
And then they saw something amazing.
在科学家观察双缝的时候
When scientists were watching the holes,
电子表现得象粒子
the electrons behaved like particles,
在屏幕那里形成了
forming the baseball-like pattern
类似于棒球实验的图案
on the screen back there.
但当科学家把眼光从双缝移开
But when the scientists weren't watching,
看到的却是电子象波浪
then the electrons behaved like waves.
它们在屏幕上形成的图案
They formed a pattern that looked like
看起来象波形的干涉图
the interference pattern produced by waves on a screen.
这真是奇怪
That's really strange.
你看到的东西 决定于你是否盯着看
What you see depends on whether you're watching or not.
如果盯着看
If you're watching,
你看到的是粒子象棒球
you see the particle-like behavior like baseballs.
如果你不是盯着看 就会看到波形
If you're not watching, you see a wavelike behavior.
但你不能两种情况都同时做
But not both at the same time.
这种现象只能用震惊来形容
This was nothing less than astounding.
人们通过观察
Observation seems to change
改变了对次原子粒子世界的认识
the nature of subatomic particles.
不可思议的是 当我们不盯着看
Mysteriously, when we're not looking,
好象是波
things are waves.
当我们盯着看 好象是粒子
When we are looking, they look like particles.
所以电子
So even an electron,
在我们眼中只是类似于粒子
which seems to us like a particle,
在不盯着看的时候 它呈现波的特性
has wavelike properties when we're not looking at it.
事实就是 当我们不盯着看
The fact that when we don't look,
电子表现为从双缝都穿过去
the electron appears to go through both holes,
但当我们盯着看
but when we do look,
通常只能看到它穿过这个或那个缝
we always see it go through one hole or the other
这种现象 我们称为"量子谜"
is what we call the quantum enigma.
观察方式的不同
How could our decision
我们对于事物变化的判断
about whether to observe something
是否应该不同呢？
change how that something acts?
这里有一个技术上的说法
There is a technical explanation.
要得出结论
To make an observation,
你必须要考虑系统的因素
you somehow have to interact with a system.
比方说 你用光线去照射它
For example, you have to shine light on it,
那么你的结论就得考虑光线的影响
which then bounces off, and you observe the light.
我们之所以说棒球落在这里或那里
That's how we can tell that a baseball is here or there:
是因为我们不考虑光线的因素
we bounce light off of it.
对宏观的颗粒来说
Well, for macroscopic particles,
光线的影响微乎其微
that doesn't disturb them very much.
但对微观粒子
But for microscopic particles,
光的因素
the act of bouncing the light off of the particle
会引起其位置和移动方式的变化
changes where it is and how it's moving.
所以 在微观世界里
So in the microscopic universe,
光子与次原子
where photons of light are about the same size
是一般大小
as subatomic particles,
当它们照亮粒子
these photons have a big impact
我们才能看得见粒子
when they illuminate the particles
因此它们有着重要影响
so we can see them.
但这样还回答不了
But this doesn't answer the question
"为什么光只是改变了次原子的方位？"
"Why doesn't the light simply change the direction of the subatomic particles?
"为什么观察方式不同 看到的情况不同？"
"Why does observation actually change the nature of what is being observed?"
答案很简单 "不知道"
The short answer is, "We don't know."
这是量子力学根本性的谜团
This is the fundamental mystery of quantum mechanics,
它是量子力学为什么特别的原因
the reason why quantum mechanics is difficult.
真是不可思议
Mysteriously, when we look at things,
盯着看 看到的是粒子
we see particles.
不盯着看 却是波
Then when we're not looking, things are waves.
这个现象
This is something
科学家们迄今为止 已激烈争吵了
we scientists have argued passionately about now
将近一百年
for almost a hundred years.
还没有达成一致
And there's still no consensus.
这些问题在一个世纪前被提出来
When they were first released a century ago,
让最聪明的科学家
these test results were enough to unsettle
也感到十分迷惑
the brightest mind in science.
爱因斯坦说
Einstein said,
"我不相信量子物理"
"I don't believe in quantum physics,
"因为我相信 我不抬头看月亮"
"because I believe the Moon is there
"它还是会在那里"
even when I'm not looking at it."
爱因斯坦的言下之意
Einstein was of course referring
就是说月亮出现的地方
to the implications of the theory
与是否在观察它
that the Moon really isn't anywhere
没有任何关系
until it's observed.
但是 双缝实验
However, the double-hole experiment's
令人难以置信的神奇远不止于此
mind-boggling conclusions don't end there.
由于近来的技术进步 科学家们
In recent years, technology has allowed scientists
让这个实验来了一个华丽的演变
to perform a fascinating variation of the test.
把问题扩大到了时间的范畴
Its results call into question our perception of time itself.
这象是双缝实验的
This is like a high-tech version
高科技版本
of the double-hole experiment.
电子冲向开有双缝的屏障
Electrons are being fired toward a barrier with two holes in it.
科学家们改为观察
But the scientists can delay their decision
电子穿过双缝之后
about whether to observe the electrons
撞击屏幕之前
until after they've passed through the holes,
的相关表现
but before they hit the screen.
这就象我在棒球场上
It's as though I'm on a baseball field
把棒球投向有两个洞的屏障
and there's a baseball being pitched toward the barrier with the holes in it.
我闭上双眼
But my eyes are closed,
所以它象波浪一样通过两个洞
so it goes through and it behaves like a wave.
但接下来 在它撞击屏幕前的最后一刻
But then, at the last second before it hits the screen,
我睁开双眼 专心观察它
I open my eyes and decide to observe it.
在这一刹那
At that moment,
电子就是粒子
the electrons, in essence, become particles
而且从离开电子枪的那一刻起
and seemingly always were particles
它们看起来都是粒子
from the time they left the electron gun.
所以好象是在通过双缝之前
So it's as though they went back in time
它们及时地后退了
to before they went through the holes
去决定穿过哪一个缝
and decided to go through one or the other,
它们不是象波一样
not through both, as they would have,
同时穿过双缝
had they been behaving like waves.
这真让人疯狂
That's really crazy!
其奥妙在于
That's the enigma:
我们选择怎样的实验方式
that our choice of what experiment to do
去确定电子当前的状态
determines the prior state of the electron.
某种因素在影响着它
Somehow or other we've had an influence on it
让它产生时光倒流的现象
which appears to travel backwards in time.
科学家们并没有由这些神奇现象出发
Scientists are only beginning to grasp
去开展时光旅行的研究
what these microscopic mysteries mean for time travel
去改变我们世界的过去
and changing the past in our everyday world.
但非常确切的是
But one thing is clear.
次原子世界的运行规律暗示着
The rules that govern this subatomic world
微观宇宙如同科幻小说一般
hint at a universe that's just as mysterious
充满着神秘
as science fiction.
其实 量子物理可能会让人联想到
In fact, quantum physics may suggest
真实事物只不过是想象力虚构出来的东西
that reality is simply a figment of our imagination.
在发现微观宇宙的神奇之后
After discovering mysteries in the microscopic universe,
科学家们想要尽快去弄清楚
scientists wanted to quickly unravel,
去研究和揭示它们
study, and solve them.
但当他们试图精确了解
But as they tried to figure out exactly what was going on
这个陌生的次原子世界
in this strange subatomic realm,
他们被意外的事情打乱了阵脚
they found something completely unexpected.
自然界拒绝告诉他们
Nature refused to tell them.
在微观世界
When we descend into the microscopic world,
我们会发现所有需要测量的参数
we find that there's a fundamental uncertainty
都具有不确定性
in essentially all quantities that we wish to measure.
这不是测量方法的原因
And it's not a problem with the measurement process.
而是自然界本身不知道怎样测量
It's that nature herself does not know.
这被称为"测不准原理"
Scientists call this the uncertainty principle.
正如奇怪的名字
And as strange as it is,
它可能是关于微观宇宙的
it may be the most profound concept
最深奥的概念
to emerge from the microscopic universe.
我们对事物的认识 不能绝对化
We simply cannot know anything with absolute certainty.
在平常的世界里
In our everyday world,
我们自认为了解许多身边的东西
we think we know a lot about the things around us.
比如
We can actually locate,
我们能找到这个母球的位置
for example, the position of this cue ball
用一定的速度去撞击它
and strike it at a certain speed,
这样
which we know,
我们就能让它撞向其它球
and we can use that to collide it into other balls,
从而开始球赛
and go ahead and play a game of pool.
但如果把所有的东西
But what actually happens
都缩小万亿倍 那会怎样呢？
if we shrink everything down trillions of times?
现在假设这些台球
In that world, these pool balls
就是次原子微粒
are now actually like subatomic particles.
在这个微观领域里
In this microscopic realm,
量子物理学家发现
quantum physicists have found
由于粒子的波状特性
they simply cannot determine with any precision
他们实在是没法精准测量
where these particles are located
它们的具体参数
because of their wavelike qualities.
而且更奇怪的是
And what's even stranger:
如果科学家们试图困住一个粒子
if scientists try to box in a particle,
它总会产生足够的能量
it will always generate enough energy
在它的位置和速度被测定之前
to break out of the box before its position and speed
逃出包围圈
have been determined.
"测不准原理"宣称
The uncertainty principle says
自然界不会允许它的基本要素
nature will not allow its fundamental elements
被困住
to be boxed in.
所以在微观世界
So because in the microscopic world
因为粒子会受到
because particles will interact
一套完全不同的
with a completely different set of rules,
量子物理规则的影响
the rules of quantum physics,
微型台球带来的是一场完全不同的球赛
microscopic pool will be a completely different game.
微观宇宙的不确定性
The uncertainty of the microscopic universe
使粒子位置的范围弹性很大
extends far beyond the location of particles.
这也适用于每一样东西 包括粒子的能量
It applies to everything, including a particle's energy.
由此引发了一个令人震惊的
And this gives rise to a stunning phenomenon
被称为"量子隧道"的现象
called quantum tunneling.
在经典物理学上
In classical physics,
如果你把球投向墙壁
if you throw a ball at a wall
由于你的力度不足够大
and you don't throw it hard enough,
它穿透不了墙壁 会反弹回来
it won't go through the wall; it will bounce back.
但如果它是一个电子
But if it's an electron
虽然你用的力度
and you don't throw it hard enough
也不足以让它穿透墙壁
to go through the wall,
但它会穿透过去
it might go through anyway.
这就是"量子隧道"现象
We call that quantum tunneling.
这怎么可能呢？
How can this be possible?
它听起来很离奇
It may sound bizarre,
唯一的解释就是
but one way to explain quantum tunneling
微观宇宙的不确定性
is that the uncertainty of the microscopic universe
允许粒子从未来借取能量
allows a particle to borrow energy
去冲破障碍
from the future to breach the barrier
在到达另一边之后
and then pay it back
再把能量还回去
after it gets to the other side.
电子的确是到达了
The electron actually already is
墙壁的另一边
on the other side of the wall,
因此 它能够穿越墙壁
and therefore, it can go through it
并出现在另一边
and appear on the other side of the wall.
自从一个世纪前
Ever since these wonders
这种微观世界的奇妙被发现以来
of the microscopic world were discovered a century ago,
人们想象着 量子隧道
people have asked if quantum tunneling
加上同时出现在多个地方
being in multiple places at the same time
以及时光倒流的特性
and what appears to be traveling backwards in time
能否让我们的日常世界趋向完美
can be achieved in our everyday world.
一些科学家说 我们永远不能
Some scientists say we'll never be able
让棒球穿过坚固的障碍
to throw a baseball through a solid barrier.
一个棒球由数量庞大的粒子构成
A baseball is a huge number of particles.
你要让所有的粒子
You would need all of them
全体突然地出现在另一边
to collectively suddenly appear in another place
这个棒球才能作为一个整体出现在另一边
for the baseball, as a whole, to appear in another place.
这是绝不可能的事情
And that's just extraordinarily unlikely.
单个的电子或质子可以这样做
A single electron or a single proton can do this.
但大的微粒
But the bigger your particle,
或者是微粒的大集合
or the bigger the collection of particles,
发生隧道效应非常困难
the more difficult that process of tunneling is.
然而 越来越多的物理学家
However, a growing number of physicists
正在发展一个更反常的理论
are developing a more outrageous theory
去解释发生的事情
for what's going on.
这些微小的粒子
We know that these tiny particles
能够在两个地方同时出现
can be in two places at the same time.
而我是由这些粒子构成的
But, hey, I'm made of these kinds of particles.
那么我也能在两个地方同时出现
So if they can be in two places at once, so can I.
科学家称这种理论为
Scientists call this
量子物理的多世界理论
the many-worlds interpretation of quantum physics.
他们说 就象双缝实验中的电子
They say, just like the electron in the double-hole experiment,
人类也能同时存在于多个地方
human beings are all in multiple places at the same time.
在任何时候 任何一个"我"做了一个决定
They say anytime anyone makes a decision,
实际上不是跳过其它的"我"来做决定
we don't actually choose one option over another.
相反地 是"我们"一起做决定
Instead, we do them both,
只是在发生的过程中 有轻微的差异
in slightly different versions of reality.
你用头脑思考
What happens when you use your mind
然后下决心
and your will to decide things is,
最后作出许多抉择
you end up actually making many choices at once,
所有的这些会被不同的平行宇宙了解到
and all of them become realized in different parallel universes.
按照量子物理的多世界假说
The many-worlds hypothesis of quantum physics
我在这个宇宙世界里
says that when I throw a curveball,
投出了一个弧线球
I do so only in this universe.
在另一个宇宙 我可能投出的是快球
In another universe, I might be throwing a fastball.
而在另外的又一个宇宙
And in still another one, I throw a knuckleball
我投出了平生第一个不旋转的球
for the first time in my life.
在另外另外的宇宙
And in yet another universe,
我把球投出了界外
I heave this ball to the outfield.
在多世界假说中
In the many-worlds hypothesis,
所有这些选择
all of these choices are outcomes
都是在平行宇宙里发生的结果
that occur in universes that are parallel to our own-
不只是发生在我们的世界里
just not in ours, but in parallel universes.
这就是多世界假说告诉我们的事情
That's what the many-worlds hypothesis tells us.
这好象是牵强附会
This may sound far-fetched,
但理论物理的许多演算表明
but an impressive array of theoretical physicists
它就是微观世界运转的法则
believe it's the way the microscopic world works.
如果它正确 这个惊人的理论所牵涉的
If it's true, the implications of this startling theory
就远不是棒球场这么简单了
go far beyond the baseball diamond.
在本质上 它暗示着
In essence, it suggests there are universes
存在这样的宇宙
parallel to our own in which
纳粹打赢了二战
the Nazis won World War II.
或是美国政府
And in another, the American government
挫败了911劫机者
foiled the 9/1 1 hijackers.
世贸中心依然屹立在曼哈顿
So the world trade center still stands in Manhattan.
如果从表面去理解量子力学
If you take quantum mechanics absolutely at face value,
带着量子力学的思维
it says that every time you observe
去观察每一样事物
something quantum-mechanical,
你会发现有两个不同的你
you become two different copies of yourself.
一个这样做
There's the copy that got one answer
另一个那样做
and a copy that got another answer.
这暗示着其实有许多不同的
It just implies there's a huge number
你本人的拷贝
of other copies of you
在各自的宇宙里
that saw slightly different things happen
有着轻微不同的际遇
in the universe.
目前 微观世界的古怪
These days, it's completely accepted
已经被人们完全接受
that the microworld is weird.
许多人希望这种古怪
Many people had hoped that this weirdness
能被局限在微观世界里
could be confined to the microworld
让我们这些庞然大物不受影响
so that big things like us would be immune to it
总是存在于单一的地方
and always be in a single place.
但现实告诉我们 这种想法
But it's become clear now that that hope...
很幼稚
Was naive.
这种古怪是不受限制的
The weirdness can't be confined.
让人如痴如醉的
The fascinating debate
关于多世界理论的
about the many-worlds interpretation
剧烈争论会持续下去
of quantum physics
除非物理学家们全部解开
will rage until physicists finally solve
微观宇宙的奥秘
the mysteries of the microscopic universe.
然而 一些天文学家断定
However, some astronomers are concluding
我们永远不能充分解释
that we will never be able to fully explain
这些奥秘的任何一个
any of these mysteries,
这是因为 按照他们的计算
because, according to their calculations,
大多数主宰着宇宙的物质
the vast majority of matter holding the universe together
以我们永远无法解释的大尺寸方式存在着
exists in a higher dimension that we can never explore.
如果微观世界里
If there's anything in the microscopic universe
还存在着比量子微粒更奇怪
stranger than quantum particles,
属于从未被科学家发现过的神秘物质
it's the mysterious matter that scientists have never seen
就会在太阳系 银河系这些天体的构成中
but that plays a crucial role in the formation of planets,
表现出关键性的作用
solar systems, and galaxies.
天文学家确信 宇宙里存在这样的物质
Astronomers know that there's all sorts of matter out there
施加着引力的影响
that exerts a gravitational influence
但我们不能看到它们
but that we can't see.
这些物质被称为"暗物质"
We call that dark matter.
如果没有暗物质 那我就不会存在
I wouldn't exist if it weren't for dark matter,
因为暗物质具有这样的能力
because dark matter has this nurturing force
可以把物质聚集在一起 形成结构
of bringing things together to form structure,
比如形成
to form galaxies,
生命所必需的星系结构
which are absolutely necessary for life.
在宇宙里具有明显引力的物质当中
Dark matter makes up a staggering 85%
暗物质所占的比例惊人
of the gravitationally attractive stuff
达到了85%
in the universe.
如果暗物质是某些种类的微粒
If the dark matter is some kind of particle,
那么通常情况下 每一秒钟穿过我身体的
then typically, millions of dark matter particles
暗物质粒子就有数百万
will pass through me every second.
但是 即使知道了暗物质的存在
But even though they know dark matter exists,
天文学家还是被微观世界的神秘所困惑
astronomers have been confounded by a microscopic mystery:
它是什么？
what is it?
一开始 他们认为这是普通的物质
At first, they thought it was ordinary matter that,
只是由于某种原因看不到它
for some reason, they couldn't see.
进行研究之后
But what happened was,
天文学家们得出一个结论
astronomers went and took an inventory.
宇宙里有许多的普通物质
We know how much ordinary matter there is in the universe.
所谓的"普通物质" 我们基本上是指原子
By "ordinary matter," we basically mean atoms,
它们是由质子中子和电子组成
things that are made out of protons, neutrons, and electrons,
这些基本微粒
the elementary particles that go into
组成你 我 地球上的每一样东西
making you, me, everything on Earth.
但这样还不行
And it just doesn't measure up.
构成宇宙的总体
There's not nearly enough ordinary matter
只有普通物质还不够
in the universe to make up the total.
这个结论很怪诞
This conclusion was bizarre.
微观宇宙的大多数物质怎么可能
How could most of the matter in the microscopic universe
不是由质子 中子和电子构成呢？
not be made of protons, neutrons, and electrons?
人们非常惊骇地发现
It's been quite shocking to discover
这些原子竟然只构成了
that these atoms actually make up
宇宙里的一小部分物体
just a small minority of all the stuff in the universe.
我们看不见的
There's six times more
完全不同的物质
of an altogether different substance
是看得见的物质的六倍还要多
which is invisible to us.
有趣的是 科学家让我们
It's interesting to think that science has brought us
认识到
to the point where we realize
我们不但不是宇宙的中心
not only are we not the center of the universe;
甚至不是
we're not even made of the same stuff
由构成大部分宇宙的物质所构成
as the universe is made of, for the most part.
宇宙的绝大多数物质
Most of the stuff in the universe
是暗物质
is this dark matter,
它是某些粒子
and it's some small particle
存在于我们的直觉之外
beyond the reach of our direct detection.
一些理论物理学家
Some theoretical physicists
猜测暗物质可能是由中微子
speculated that dark matter might be made of neutrinos-
这种极小的
tiny particles
比电子小一千倍的粒子所构成
a thousand times smaller than an electron
这样就能符合暗物质的许多已知参数
that fit many of the known characteristics of dark matter.
我们知道中微子的存在
We know neutrinos exist.
它们有质量
And they have mass.
使重量得到增加
They contribute weight, so maybe we're done.
但这些不是中微子
But now it's turned out that they're not neutrinos.
绝大多数的暗物质估计不是正常的中微子
Most of the dark matter is probably not normal neutrinos,
因为它们移动得非常 非常快
because they travel very, very quickly.
会彻底摧毁
And they wipe out the formation
宇宙历史早期的
of what's called large-scale structure,
被称为"大尺度结构"的
the clumping of material on the scale of galaxies,
星系里的物质团
early in the universe's history.
如果宇宙里充满着
So it would be much harder to produce galaxies
许多的中微子
if the universe is filled
那么就会严重影响到星系的产生
with lots and lots of neutrinos zooming around.
所以暗物质不是普通的物质
So the dark matter is not ordinary matter.
它不是中微子
It's not neutrinos.
它是某种全新类型的
It's some wholly new kind of particle
尚未被我们了解的微粒
that we haven't detected yet.
它应当是某种奇怪的次原子微粒
It has to be some sort of weird subatomic particle
源于宇宙极高温 极高密度时
Ieft over from the big bang,
发生的大爆炸
when the universe was very hot and dense.
当时产生了各种各样的微粒
A whole zoo of particles was created.
绝大部分被湮没或合并到其它的微粒中
Most of them annihilated or decayed into other particles.
但有一些遗留了下来
But some were left over,
那就是我们所说到的暗物质
and they are what are thought to be the dark matter.
这种奇异的微观粒子是怎样的呢？
But what could this exotic microscopic particle be?
由于科学家对它一无所知
Since it's nothing known to science,
天文学家们认为它是一种全新的粒子
astronomers proposed an entirely new particle
具有暗物质的所有特性
that embodied all of dark matter's characteristics
于是 天文学家开始在宇宙里寻觅它的踪迹
and then began searching the universe for it.
并把它称为WIMP
They call it a WIMP,
即"大质量弱相互作用粒子"
a Weakly Interacting Massive Particle.
WIMP假说面临着一个问题
One of the problems with the WIMP hypothesis
能不能在实验室里了解WIMP粒子
is that we've never actually detected a WIMP in a laboratory.
事实上 有几个实验
In fact, there's several experiments
准备在地下实验室里
going on right this minute
寻找WIMP粒子
to look for WIMPS in underground laboratories.
你可以对它们使用粒子加速器
And you'd also like to make them in particle accelerators,
比如日内瓦的大型强子对撞机
Iike the Large Hadron Collider in Geneva.
所以 如果它们就是答案的话
So there's a multipronged attack to detect WIMPs directly
可以有多种方法去了解它们
if they're the right answer.
如果科学家发现了暗物质的证据
If scientists find evidence of dark matter,
就相当于找到了另一个世界
will they also find evidence of another world
就会发现暗行星
of dark planets...
暗生物
dark life-forms...
和组成暗物质的元素吗？
and a dark matter table of elements?
我不认为暗物质粒子
I don't think they are like us,
象我们的世界一样
in that the dark matter particles
能够形成行星等等
can form planets and so on,
因为 如果它们可以
because if they could,
那么太阳系的绝大多数行星
then we would expect most of the planets in our solar system
实际上就是由暗物质构成
to actually be made of dark matter.
我认为更有可能的是
But I think it's much more likely
暗域是由许多种不同的粒子复合而成
that the dark sector is many different kinds of particles
而不是只由一种粒子构成
that are much more complex than just one.
然而 现代科学
However, modern science
还没能发现
still has not found evidence
这种神秘的微型材料
of this mysterious microscopic material.
越来越多的科学家坚信
And a growing number of scientists argue
这是因为它不是别的东西
that's because it's not something else;
它是别处的东西
it's somewhere else,
来自于另外的世界
Iike other dimensions.
人们非常严肃地认为
People have taken very seriously
暗物质来自于另外的世界
the idea that the dark matter comes from other dimensions,
或者是说明有普通的粒子
or represents ordinary particles
跑到另外的世界去了
that are actually moving in the other dimensions.
那个世界里的东西
The thing about other dimensions are,
我们看不到
we don't see them,
与它们没有强烈的相互作用
we don't interact with them very strongly,
所以它们自然地隐身起来
so they're a natural place to put the dark matter.
我们把星系和星系团里的
It's conceivable that the gravitational influence
重力的影响
in galaxies and clusters of galaxies
归根于我们宇宙中的暗物质
that we attribute to dark matter in our own universe,
其来源于另外的世界里
is actually caused by concentrations of matter
可以被我们感觉到
in other dimensions
却永远不会被我们发现
that are felt within our dimensions
的浓聚物
but will never be discovered within our dimensions
因为它们事实上是其它地方的
because they're actually somewhere else.
无论它是什么样或是在哪里
Whatever or wherever it is,
许多物理学家坚信
many physicists are confident
他们终究会完全了解
they'll eventually discover a complete solution
暗物质的神秘
to the dark matter mystery...
除非它只是简单地
unless, they say, it simply exists
以一个极小的尺寸存在着
at an incredibly small size,
小到人们没办法去研究
far smaller than humans have ever been able to explore.
这就带来了一个问题
That raises the question:
在微观宇宙里
"What does exist
物体能够小到哪种程度？
at the smallest scales of the microscopic universe?"
德克萨斯州休斯顿的研究人员詹森.L
That's what viewer Jason L. from Houston, Texas,
很关注这个问题
wanted to...
询问宇宙
詹森 我向您请教那个问题
Jason, I'm glad you asked that question.
宇宙里最小的东西
The smallest things in the universe
是那些基本的次原子粒子
are the fundamental subatomic particles,
比如电子
Iike electrons
或者构成质子和中子的夸克粒子
or the quarks that make up protons and neutrons
或者中微子
or neutrinos.
现在 所有这些粒子被想象为
Now, all these particles are thought to be
以不同的方式摆动着的微型物体
different vibrational modes of a little tiny entity
被称为弦
called a string,
它是极微小的能量团
a little tiny package of energy.
是构成别的一切物质
And that, then, is the smallest thing
的最小单位
from which everything else is made.
询问宇宙
科学家们已经开始努力去
Scientists have just started
研究弦
trying to explore strings,
以及微观宇宙里其它极为细小的物质
and other incredibly small stuff in the microscopic universe.
他们的发现
And what they found
将是找到另一个世界的
offers tantalizing clues
重要线索
to a world beyond.
他们对微观宇宙的研究
As they delve into smaller and smaller spaces
深入到了越来越小的范围
in the microscopic universe,
科学家们已经成功观察到原子的内部
scientists have successfully looked inside atoms.
如果继续深入研究下一层的次原子
But what exists if we continue our fantastic voyage
那里会有一些什么呢？
still deeper into this subatomic netherworld?
比电子还小的领域
Even scales that are smaller than the electron
有着大量的未知奥秘
are really a vast unexplored territory,
其未知的程度 远甚于太阳系 银河系
more so than solar systems or galaxies
乃至于宇宙
or even the universe,
因为我们可以观察行星 恒星
because we can make observations of planets and stars
星系和宇宙
and galaxies and the universe,
但难以开展实验
but it's hard to conduct experiments
让我们能直接探测
that allow us to directly explore
微小的时间和空间
tiny scales in time and space.
你想要精确知道微观世界
Essentially, what you need to examine
就必须要有极端灵敏的工具
the microscopic world is a sharper and sharper tool,
这样才能让你
something that actually allows you
得到数值非常小的数据
to distinguish the details down at that very small level.
但在努力探测比原子还小的空间的时候
But as scientists try to probe spaces smaller than the atom,
科学家们不能够让足够的光
they cannot possibly focus enough light
去照亮它们
to illuminate them.
他们需要更强劲的东西
They need something more powerful.
要观察更精细 就需要更多能量
To look more finely, you need more energy.
我们可以通过各种高能装置
We can go to incredibly small details
去得到更小的数据
using high-energy devices of various kinds.
当今工艺水平之最
Now, the state of the art
当数粒子加速器
are actually particle accelerators.
我们使用基本粒子
We use elementary particles
通过碰撞去探测
to actually probe the structure of other elementary particles
其它基本粒子的结构
by colliding them together,
在各种能量等级下
Ietting them interact with each other
让它们相互作用 观察释放出来的东西
and then seeing what comes out at various energy scales.
故此 我们在碰撞实验中
So we can continue this process
使用的能量越高
of examining smaller and smaller distances
才能继续探测
in space and time
越小的
by actually going to higher and higher energy
空间和时间
with collider experiments.
然而 世界上最大的粒子加速器
However, the world's largest particle accelerators
也没有足够的能量去探测
have not yet generated enough energy to probe things
原子内部比基本粒子小得多的东西
much smaller than the elementary particles inside atoms.
即使如此
Even so,
科学家们相信还存在着
scientists believe something exists
更小的物质
at even smaller scales,
它们的尺寸十分小
at a size so tiny, the human mind
以至于人类不可能理解
cannot possibly comprehend it.
物理学家们现在正努力去探究
Physicists are now trying to understand
"普朗克长度"
what's called the Planck length,
即是10的-33次方厘米
10 to the minus 33-power centimeters.
它比一个电子的尺寸
That's 20 factors of 10-
还要小10-20次方
20 orders of magnitude smaller than an electron.
相比而言 电子就大得很夸张了
Now, an electron is yea big, and I exaggerate a lot.
所以 比起任何可以实际测量的物体
So the Planck length is just almost unimaginably smaller
普朗克长度小得难以形容
than any objects we can actually measure.
尽管如此 物理学家正在试图
Nevertheless, physicists are trying
涉足其中
to deal with these scales.
这正是弦理论的范畴
And that's what string theory is all about.
弦理论认为
String theory says that everything
一切我们看作是粒子的东西
that we think of as a particle
实际上是极小的振动着的环状的弦
is actually a tiny vibrating loop of string.
为了说明它有多小
To get an idea of how tiny it is,
我找来了一个点眼药器
I have here an eyedropper.
我们准备滴出一滴水
We're going to put out one drop of water.
其里面大约有百万兆又百万兆的
That has about a trillion trillion atoms
氢原子和氧原子
of hydrogen and oxygen.
现在假设让一个氢原子
Now imagine taking one hydrogen atom
变大一百亿倍
and blowing it up by 1 0 billion times.
它的直径就会大约有0.5米
It becomes about 1/2 a meter across.
你可能会问
And you might say,
"现在我们能看到这个氢原子"
"Can we now see the individual strings
"里面的弦吗？"
inside that hydrogen atom?"
答案是"不能"
But the answer is no.
假设让这个氢原子继续变大
We can continue to make it bigger,
大到太阳系这么大
make one hydrogen atom the size of the solar system.
里面的弦还是小到看不见
The strings are still too small to be seen.
只有当原子的尺寸
It's only when we make that atom
大到我们看得见的宇宙这么大
the size of our observable universe,
弦才能被看到
that a string becomes macroscopically large.
如果一个氢原子和整个看得见的宇宙一样大
If one hydrogen atom is as big as the whole observable universe,
一个弦有多大呢？
how big is a string?
它只有这些树中的一棵这么大
Only about the size of one of these trees.
人类能够恰如其分地描述
The amazing thing is that we human beings
如此微小世界里的情形
can even talk sensibly about what exists
真是很了不起的事情
at this microscopic scale.
科学家们不单是能恰当地描述它
Not only can scientists talk sensibly;
而且也发展出许多理论去解释其运行机制
they've also formulated theories about what happens down there.
它是所有科学里
This is really one of the holy grails
被追求的终极目标之一
of all of science.
我们认为普通的空间和时间
We think that ordinary space and time
在普朗克长度上终止
cease to exist at the Planck length.
我们不能知道它们的具体情形
What we don't know is what takes their place.
我们需要透过更基本的事物
We need to replace our idea of space itself
各种不同的尺度
by something more fundamental,
或者是完全不同的思想观念
something that might involve different numbers of dimensions
去改变我们关于空间本身的认识
or just a different concept entirely.
有一种可能是 普朗克长度上的空间
One possibility is that space at the Planck length
类似于足球场上的格子
resembles the grid on a football field.
码线就是我们宇宙的构造
The yard lines are the fabric of our universe,
在其彼此间没有任何东西
and there's simply nothing in between.
时间应当是从一个单独的点
It could be that time jumps
跳跃到另一个点
from one discrete point to another,
中间没有任何过渡
and there are no steps in between.
就象是量子力学上的蚂蚁
And, like, little quantum mechanical ants
从一个孤立的地点挖掘地道
could tunnel from one spot on the grid
去到另一个孤立的地方
to another spot on the grid
而不需要进入
without ever going
两者之间的空间
into the intervening space in between.
为什么？
Why?
因为两者之间没有空间
'Cause there isn't any intervening space in between.
无论是什么存在于这个极小尺度上
Whatever exists at this incredibly small scale,
大多数科学家相信 空间和时间的概念
most scientists believe that the concepts of space and time
延伸到另一个缩小的宇宙里
segue into another kind of universe
没有任何意义
where shrinking smaller is a meaningless concept.
应该说 时间和空间
It could be that time and space
具有我们所说的
are what we call emergent properties
"宇宙的突现性"
of the universe,
但到了非常小的空间
but that if you go to very small spatial scales,
或者是间隔非常短的时间
or very small intervals of time,
时空的概念就被打破了
the concepts of time and space break down.
变得没有意义
They don't make sense.
科学家们认为 在普朗克长度下的环境
Scientists say the conditions at the Planck length
可能非常类似于宇宙大爆炸前的环境
may be very similar to those that existed
在那个时候
before the big bang,
宇宙里的一切
when everything in our universe
很可能集中到一个微小的点上
was probably concentrated in a microscopic pinpoint.
这与宇宙在最小尺度时
Maybe the same answers to the question
发生了什么事情
about what happens to the universe
可能是同一个答案吗？
at the very smallest scales
也许这能让我们知道
may also be connected to knowing,
宇宙大爆炸之前的样子
what was the universe like before the big bang?
它在大爆炸的时候 才开始存在吗？
Did it just come into being at the big bang,
或者是别的不同的东西
or was there something different
在我们知道的大爆炸之后
which then turned into the universe
才变成宇宙？
that we're familiar with at the big bang?
一切我们不能回答的问题
These are all questions we don't know the answer to
全都与普朗克长度上的情况
but are all connected to the issue
有着紧密的联系
of what's going on at the Planck scale.
你可能会想 微小的普朗克长度上的东西
You might think that these tiny Planck-scale things
与我们这些庞然大物无关
have nothing to do with us, who are much bigger.
但事实上 它在一切事情上影响着我们
But actually, it has everything to do with us.
它是我们的起源
It's our origins.
我们整个宇宙 如果往前推算
Our entire universe, if we extrapolate backwards,
曾经比普朗克长度还小
would have been smaller than the Planck length.
无论在最小的次原子世界里
Whatever exists at the smallest scales
存在着什么东西
of the subatomic world,
也不管它们的情况如何
and however these things behave,
科学家们认为 他们必须全部了解它们
scientists say they must make sense of it all
才有可能去了解整个宇宙
before they can possibly comprehend the cosmos above,
人类行为
human behavior,
以及大爆炸之前可能存在的东西
and what might have existed before the big bang.
这就是研究微观宇宙里
It's a mind-boggling amount of information
难以想象的小空间
tucked inside an unimaginably small space
的宏伟意义
of our microscopic universe.